Guide to the Rose Pastor Stokes Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
- Writings, 1900, 1903, 1908-1909, 1912, 1914-1917, 1922, 1926, 1933, 1958; Series II
  2. There is also an incomplete second draft of the RPS autobiography in the RPS Papers (Series II, folder 6C) which was removed from the Victor J. Jerome Papers. (A photocopy of this draft remains in the Jerome Papers.)
  3. The second draft differs somewhat from the first draft through p. 47 with different annotations, revisions, and in some cases, extra paragraphs - though the text is basically the same. From p. 48 to p. 111, the text is the same, though again with different annotations. From p. 111 to p. 119 the text varies somewhat. From p. 120-p. 132 the text of the two drafts is again the same, still however with different annotations, with the second draft being more heavily revised and annotated than the first. It is in this section that the second draft appears to be, in part, an actual revision of the first draft, incorporating to some degree revisions suggested in the latter.
  4. The first draft ends at p. 132; the second draft continues to p. 239 with page numbering gaps between pp. 143 and 178, and between pp. 195 and 220. It is difficult to tell whether these are substantive textual gaps or merely numbering gaps.
  5. It is obvious then that the second draft is the more complete and it is probably the latest revision of the autobiography.
  Further information about the autobiography is available in Appendix III in the finding aid in the repository. Consult Reference Archivist for assistance.
  - Articles, reviews, letters to the editor, 1908, 1914-1916 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Articles and sketches printed in The Jewish Daily News, 1903, undated (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Article: "There are Few Bad Divorces," Collier's, 1926 February 13 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Article: "The Welfare of Mothers and Infants in Russia", undated (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Article: "Woman's Committees", undated (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Autobiography, incomplete first draft, 1879-1905 (Box 6, Folder 6A)
  - Autobiography, incomplete first draft (photocopy), 1879-1905 (Box 6, Folder 6B)
  - Autobiography, incomplete second draft., 1879-1915 (Box 6, Folder 6C)
  - Autobiography, excerpt appearing in Jewish Currents, 1958 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Autobiography, excerpt re: the waiters' strike, (1912?) (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Concert notes: "notes on the Russian Songs", 1917 (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Diary, 1933 (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - Divorce, undated (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - Letter: The Parlor Provocateur, includes letter from RPS, undated (Box 6, Folder 12)
  - News release: Patrick Quinlan Case, undated (Box 6, Folder 13)
  - notes, miscellaneous, undated (Box 6, Folder 14)
  - Pamphlet: "Why Study Socialism?" with letter from RPS, undated (Box 6, Folder 15)
  - Pamphlet: "Workers' International Relief", 1928 September (Box 6, Folder 16)
  - Play: "The Woman Who Wouldn't," fragment, undated (Box 6, Folder 17)
  - Poems, miscellaneous, 1908, 1914, undated (Box 6, Folder 18)
  - Poem: "The Life of You" in The Conservator, 1909 June (Box 6, Folder 19A)
  - Poem: "The Sea and I" with photograph of RPS signed by Clarence Hudson White, undated (Box 6, Folder 19B)
  - Reports: to IV Comintern Congress, 1922 November-December (Box 6, Folder 20)
  - Reports: to IV Comintern Congress, photocopies, 1922 November-December (Box 6, Folder 21)
  - Speeches, 1900, 1916 (Box 6, Folder 22)
  - Translations: Poems by Morris Rosenfeld, 1916, undated (Box 6, Folder 23)
- Printed Material, 1904-1953; Series III; 0.75; (2 boxes)
  PRINTED MATERIAL is arranged in three sections: Scrapbooks, Newspaper Clippings, and Pamphlets and Posters. Within each section, the folder titles are arranged alphabetically by subject. Material in the folders is arranged chronologically.
  The Scrapbook section contains the contents of two scrapbooks which have been removed from their bindings and placed in folders. The first scrapbook comprises newspaper clippings dated from November 1915 to January 1917. The bulk of the clippings are concerned with Rose Pastor Stokes' views on socialism, her activities in support of the dissemination of birth control information to the public, the Patrick Quinlan appeal in New Jersey, and several legal cases, including the trials of Elizabeth Gurley Flynn, Jessie Ashley, Margaret Sanger, and Emma Goldman. The second scrapbook contains newspaper clippings, dated 1916 to 1920, which concern the activities of Valdimir Resnikoff, a blind Russian baritone in whom Rose Pastor Stokes took great interest.
  Newspaper Clippings include articles about the life - both public and private - of Rose Pastor Stokes, reviews of several of her plays, her translations of Morris Rosenfeld's poetry, and articles on a plagiarism controversy involving R.H. Davis' play The Guilty Man. Also included are articles on various medical discoveries, on several labor strikes, on the theater, and some miscellaneous material. Last, there is a folder of posthumous tributes to Rose Pastor Stokes.
  The third section, Pamphlets and Posters, consists of material from various political, social, and literary organizations spanning the period from 1903 to 1932.
  - Scrapbooks
    - Newspaper clippings, November 1915-January 1917 (Box 7, Folder 1-5)
    - on Vladimir Resnikoff, 1916-1920 (Box 7, Folder 6-7)
  - Newspaper Clippings
    - Articles about RPS, 1908, 1914-1918, 1925-1926, 1930-1933, undated (Box 8, Folder 8)
    - Controversy over "The Guilty Man", 1913, 1916 (Box 8, Folder 9)
    - Medical discoveries, 1932, undated (Box 8, Folder 10)
    - Miscellaneous material, 1904, 1915-1916, 1927, 1932, undated (Box 8, Folder 11)
    - RPS' play "In April", 1915-1917 (Box 8, Folder 12)
    - RPS' play "The Saving of Martin Greer", 1914 (Box 8, Folder 13)
    - RPS' play "The Woman who Wouldn't", 1916-1917 (Box 8, Folder 14)
    - RPS' translations of "Songs of Labor", 1915 (Box 8, Folder 15)
    - Strikes, 1912, 1917, undated (Box 8, Folder 16)
    - The Theater, 1913, 1916, 1919, 1921, undated (Box 8, Folder 17)
    - Tributes to RPS, 1933, 1938, 1941, 1943, 1945-1946, 1953, undated (Box 8, Folder 18)
    - Pamphlets and Posters, 1908, 1915-1917, 1922, 1932, undated (Box 8, Folder 19)
- Subject File, 1904-1944; Series IV; 1 linear feet (3 boxes)
  The SUBJECT FILE contains material on the Rose Pastor Stokes Testimonial and Concert (1933) and the Rose Pastor Stokes Rest Home (1936). Included in the former; under the heading "Program notes," are written testimonials from a number of well-known people such as Eugene V. Debs, Elizabeth Gurley Flynn, Upton Sinclair, and Lincoln Steffens. In addition, there are minutes of various organizations, several poems by people other than Rose Pastor Stokes, legal records and documents, news releases, political campaign material for James Graham Phelps Stokes, a copy of Rose Pastor Stokes' will and miscellaneous photographs. The series is arranged alphabetically by subject.
  With the excepction of Box 9, Folders 12, 13, and 18, materials in this series are avaiable on microfilm. Patrons must use FILM HM 45 instead of the original copies.
  - Allied Professional Committee: organization meeting minutes, November 17, 1933 (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - "An Appeal to Dabs", anonymous poem, undated (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - Cards: business, calling, membership, announcements and invitations, undated (Box 9, Folder 3A)
  - "Caritas Island" Photograph of an excerpt from Rockwell Kent's, 1944 (Box 9, Folder 3B)
    Nine blueprints (copies) of the house on "Caritas Island" are in the folio.
  - Champion of Democracy autobiography, It's Me, O Lord, undated (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - Corres. re newspaper printing error on RPS, 1925 (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - Course notes: lectures by Professor Peter Tutyshkin, undated (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - Fragments of articles and stories, undated (Box 9, Folder 7A)
  - Guest book of James Graham Phelps Stokes and RPS for "Caritas Island" (photographic copy), 1905-1918 (Box 9, Folder 7B)
  - International Labor Defense: RPS Branch includes corres. to/from Jerome Romaine under alias of V.J. Jerome, 1933-1936 (Box 9, Folder 8)
    For other corres. of JIR (VJJ) see also: Family Correspondence (box 4, folder 129-132); Correspondence of Others (box 5, folder 149); Subject File, RPS Rest Home (box 11, folder 33)
  - Itinerary: RPS' Southern trip, November 20-December 17? (Box 9, Folder 9)
  - Legal Matters: "Scottsboro, Alabama Case" affidavit, 1933 (Box 9, Folder 10)
  - Legal Matters: State of Michigan vs RPS affidavits, 1930-1931 (Box 9, Folder 11)
  - Legal Record: US Circuit Court of Appeals: RPS vs United States, District Court of the US for the Western District of Missouri, 1918 (Box 9, Folder 12)
  - Legal Record: US Circuit Court of Appeals, 8th Circuit: RPS vs United States, Brief for Plaintiff in Error, 1918 (Box 9, Folder 13)
  - Letter stencils, undated (Box 9, Folder 14)
  - Miscellaneous notes, undated (Box 9, Folder 15)
  - Miscellaneous pictures, anonymous, undated (Box 9, Folder 16)
  - RPS personal finances, 1912-1913, 1915-1918, 1920-1921, 1924, 1926-1929, 1930-1932, undated (Box 9, Folder 17)
  - Photographic plate, undated (Box 9, Folder 18)
  - Photographs, 1913 (Box 10, Folder 19)
    See also: Folio
  - Photographs from the albums of James Graham Phelps Stokes and RPS, Nos. 1-49. (Box 10, Folder 20)
    See: Appendix 1
  - Photographs from the albums of James Graham Phelps Stokes and RPS, Nos. 50-99. (Box 10, Folder 21)
  - Photographs from the albums of James Graham Phelps Stokes and RPS, Nos. 100-129. (Box 10, Folder 22)
  - Photographs from the albums of James Grahams (Box 10, Folder 23a)
  - Phelps Stokes and RPS, Nos. 130-165. (Box 10, Folder 23a)
  - Photographs… Nos 166.232. (Box 10, Folder 23b)
  - Photographs of RPS by Clarence Hudson White; 3 initialled prints and 1 uninitialled print, undated (Box 10, Folder 24)
    - Copies of photographs from the newsreel films of the Fourth Comintern Congress/ Moscow-Petrograd, Nov-Dec 1922. Originals at the Hoover Institution at Stanford. (Box 10, Folder 24a)
    - No.226/Train with foreign delegates arrives at Petrograd Railroad Station (Novemeber 14, 1922). Shown on the platform are Karl Becker (Bremen), Hertha Sturm (Great Britain) Hugo Urbahns (Hamburg), Clara Zetkin (Great Britain), Rose Pastor Stokes (U.S.) and Zinoviev. (3 copies), 1922 November (Box 10, Folder 24a)
    - No.226A/Another view of the arrival showing Karl Radek (Poland), Hugo Urbahns, Clara Zetkin, Rose Pastor Stokes, Zinoviev and Hugo Eberlein (Germany), 1922 November (Box 10, Folder 24a)
    - No.226B/Another view of the arrival showing German delegates: Werner Scholem, Paul Boettcher, Fritz Heckert, Willi Munzenberg and Ernst Meyer, 1922 November (Box 10, Folder 24a)
    - No. 227/Delegates leaving railroad station, Petrograd. Dziga Vertrov, camerman. Delegates identified are: Zinoviev, Rose Pastor Stokes, Lunacharsky and Max Eastman. (3 copies), 1922 November (Box 10, Folder 24a)
    - No.228/U.S. delegates to the Congress: Martin Abern, Ludwig E. Katterfeld, Jack Johnstone, Arne Swabeck, James Cannon, Sullivan (?), Max Bedacht, Alexander Trachtenberg and Rose Pastor Stokes. (2 copies), 1922 November (Box 10, Folder 24a)
    - Celebration of 5th Anniversary of Bolshevik Revolution. Identified are: Zinoviev, Clara Zetkin, Joseph Stalin, Sen Katayama (Yale 1895 B D) and Kalinin., 1922 Nov (Box 10, Folder 24a)
  - Plans for organization, undated (Box 11, Folder 25)
  - Poem on RPS, "To a Rose," presumably written by Olive Tilford Dargan (Fielding Burke), 1904 (Box 11, Folder 26)
  - Poem on RPS …(photocopy), 1904 (Box 11, Folder 27)
  - Poem, "The Fates," by Mabel D. Curry, undated (Box 11, Folder 28)
  - Political campaign material for J. Graham Phelps Stokes, 1908 (Box 11, Folder 29)
  - Programs, 1914-1917, 1919, 1923, 1925, 1928, undated (Box 11, Folder 30)
  - Questionnaire and photostat of same, undated (Box 11, Folder 31)
  - RPS Rest Home:
    - Corres., and requests for sponsorship and replies, 1936 (Box 11, Folder 32)
    - Organizing committee corres., (includes corres. with JIR), 1936 (Box 11, Folder 33)
      For other corres. of JIR [VJJ] see also: Family Correspondence (box 4, folder 129-132); Correspondence of Others (box 5, folder 149); Subject File, International Labor Defense RPS Branch (box 9, folder 8)
    - Miscellaneous notes and bills, 1936 (Box 11, Folder 34)
    - Committee corres. with Clifford Odets, nominal chairman, 1936 (Box 11, Folder 35)
  - Reviews of plays by RPS, edited versions, 1915, undated (Box 11, Folder 36)
  - Spanish Civil War Poster, oversize. (Box DR121F0)
    See: Drawer 121 (NOT FILMED)
  - RPS Testimonial and Concert, 1933
    - Exec. Committee corres.: Dr. Maximilian Cohen, Francis Strauss (Box 11, Folder 38)
    - Minutes of Exec. Committee (Box 11, Folder 39)
    - Miscellaneous notes (Box 11, Folder 40)
    - News releases, 1933 April (Box 11, Folder 41)
    - Program notes (Box 11, Folder 42)
    - Requests for speakers, sponsors, and contributions; replies: Abbott-Gold (Box 11, Folder 43)
    - Requests for speakers, sponsors, and contributions: replies: Hale-World Telegram (Box 11, Folder 44)
    - Photostats of letters from Russian Revolutionary Writers Society, Tom Mooney (Box 11, Folder 45)
    - Statement of account and misc. receipts (Box 11, Folder 46)
    - Traubel, Horace: "Good-Bye and Hail Walt Whitman," (editor) and "Give All to Love." Gifts by the author to RPS, 1892, 1902 (Box 11, Folder 47)
    - Tribute to RPS written by Maximilian Cohen, undated (Box 11, Folder 48)
    - "The Utilization of the Photochemical (biological) Effect of the Rontgen-ray to Therapeutical Ends," by Professor Hans Holfelder, undated (Box 11, Folder 49)
    - Wilkes-Barre Incident, anonymous tracts, [1924] (Box 11, Folder 50)
    - RPS Will, includes copy of will, minutes of executors' meeting, and related correspondence, 1933 July 14; 1933-1934 (Box 11, Folder 51)
    - Stokes, Rose. Pastor, 1879-1933 TMS "I Belong to the Working Class," autobiography of Rose Pastor Stokes, 1932
- Drawings, 1923-1932; Series V; .5 linear feet (1 box and 1 folio)
  The DRAWINGS of Rose Pastor Stokes are arranged by type. Most of the material in this series is undated, unsigned, and untitled. There is some oversized material which has been placed in a folio.
  Along with drawings and sketches in various mediums, the series contains a group of sketches accompanied by short, satirical verses and photographs of drawings. About two-thirds of the original drawings represented by the photographs do not appear in the papers.
  - Line Drawings, 1924, 1926-1932, undated (Box 12, Folder 1-2)
  - Line drawings, oversize., 1924, 1926, 1928, n.d (Box 12, Folder 3)
    See: Folio
  - Photographs of drawings with comments by RPS, 1923-1926, undated (Box 12, Folder 4)
  - Political cartoon, oversize, 1924 (Box 12, Folder 5)
  - Portrait drawings, 1923-1926, 1931, undated (Box 12, Folder 6)
  - Portrait drawings, oversize, 1924, 1932, undated (Box 12, Folder 7)
  - Sketches, oversize, undated (Box 12, Folder 8)
  - Sketches and accompanying verses, undated (Box 12, Folder 9)
  - Sketches and accompanying verses, oversize. (Box 12, Folder 10)
  - Sketches and art exhibit catalog, 1926, undated (Box 12, Folder 11)
  - Sketches in crayon, 1925-1926, 1930, undated (Box 12, Folder 12)
  - Sketches in crayon, oversize., 1931, undated (Box 12, Folder 13)
  - Folio
    - Line drawings, 1924, 1926, 1928, undated (Box 12A)
    - Political cartoon, 1924 (Box 12A)
    - Portrait drawings, 1924, 1932, undated (Box 12A)
    - Sketches, undated (Box 12A)
    - Sketches and accompanying verses, undated (Box 12A)
    - Sketches in crayon, 1931, undated (Box 12A)
    - Photograph of RPS, 1913 (Box 12A)
- Additional Material
  Received from: John M. Whitcomb
  - Diary, 1913 January 5-1915 March 27
    - Electrostatic copies (Add.1984 Mar 6) (Box 13, Folder 1)
    - Original (Add.1985 Feb 4) (Box 13, Folder 2)
    - "Yale Graduates and the 5th Anniversary of the Bolshevik Revolution," by Alistair Beard Merrall (John M. Whitcomb), 1985 November 11 (Box 13, Folder 3)
      Accession 1987-M-025
    - Nine blueprints (copies) of the house on "Caritas Island", 1906 (Box 13, Folder 3)
- Additional Material, 1916-1982, undated; Accession 1992-M-032; 0.25; (1 box)
  Addition inventory by Carol King 1992 Sep
  Received from: John M. Whitcomb, 1991 Sep 15
  - Correspondence
    - Intercollegiate Socialist Society, 1917 February 13 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Ornitz, Sam, 1932 December 15 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Strunsky, Rose, 1916 November 16 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Whitcomb, John: inquiries to others re: Rose Pastor Stokes, 1936-1982, undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Genealogical research: interview notes, photocopies of legal documents, and biographical information re: the family and associates of Rose Pastor Stokes, 1918-1967, undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Photographs, undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - "Growing Up With America," by Richard Pastor, 1993 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    from Accession 1994-M-020
    Received from: Richard Pastor, 1993 Sep 8